Lost at Sea: The Search for Longitude is a adventure,
documentary, drama film directed by Peter Jones.
It was one of humankind's most epic quests - a technical problem so complex that it challenged the best minds of
its time, a problem so important that the nation that solved it would rule the economy of the world.
The problem was navigation by sea—how to know where you were when you
sailed beyond the sight of land - establishing your longitude.
While the gentry of the 18th Century looked to the stars for the answer, an English
clockmaker, John Harrison, toiled for decades to solve the problem.
His elegant solution made him an unlikely hero and remains the basis for
the most modern forms of navigation in the world today.
This film will be both a celebration of Harrison's
invention and an adventure story.
An expedition on a period sailing vessel as it sails the open sea will demonstrate
the life and death importance of finding your longitude at sea.
Narrator, played by Richard Dreyfuss.
John Harrison, played by Patrick Malahide.
Longitude: The True Story of a Lone Genius Who Solved the Greatest Scientific Problem of His Time is a 1995 best-selling book by Dava Sobel about John Harrison, an
18th-century clockmaker who created the first clock (chronometer) sufficiently accurate to be used to determine longitude at sea—an important development in navigation.
The book was made into a television series entitled Longitude.
In 1998, The Illustrated Longitude was published, supplementing the earlier text with
180 images of characters, events, instruments, maps and publications.
The film explores themes of biography, docudrama, navigation.
The tone is emotional and thought_provoking.